[Music]
foreign
I've explored the role calcium
supplements may play in reducing lead
exposure during pregnancy and
breastfeeding but this is assuming that
the supplements aren't themselves
contaminated
it all started
with an extraordinary case report
published in 1977 entitled lead
contaminated health food
a doctor prescribed a dietary supplement
for a young woman with painful periods
not just any woman though TV and film
actress Allison Hayes famous for such
roles as attack of the 50-foot woman
and not just any physician but physician
to the Stars Dr Henry Bueller who told
his patients to forget about toxic drugs
food is your best medicine which in this
case was a calcium supplement made from
horse bone she took it every day but got
weaker and sicker and by 1967 her acting
career was over when she was unable to
walk without a cane
she's not doctor after doctor after
doctor to no avail she decided she could
give up commit suicide
or figure it out herself
so she had some friends drive her to a
medical Library by then she couldn't
even walk and had to be carried in
she sat on the floor day after day and
finally came across a book on Industrial
toxicology that described what she soon
realized was a classic case of lead
poisoning she paid to have the calcium
supplement tested and indeed it was full
of lead At first she was relieved but
then the anger said in doctor after
doctor had basically dismissed her as
hysterical she had to depend on herself
to end up educating them
the Silver Lining was that the FDA in a
letter actually credited her for being a
key stimulus for their plans to look
into regulating heavy metals in foods
and supplements unfortunately the letter
arrived after she'd already died from
leukemia which may have been triggered
by the lead poisoning or the 300 x-ray
exam she got from those 22 baffled
Physicians
you'd think the supplement industry
would clean up its own act but perhaps
it's unrealistic to expect the health
food and wellness industry to dampen
their Evangelistic promotion of these
products on their own where did the lead
come from well lead get stored in your
bones and so when you eat supplements
made out of Bones you can get exposed
so was that one calcium supplement just
a tip of an iceberg at first we thought
it was just from the bone supplements
and Dolomite a mineral that can be lead
contaminated but then calcium carbonate
oyster shell calcium chelated calcium
was found to have comparable lead levels
to animal bone and so this inspired a
comprehensive survey of the lead content
of 70 different brands of calcium
supplements and lead levels varied by
almost 300 volts some of which two three
or even four times the tolerable daily
intake of lead for children especially
the most common natural source calcium
like oyster shell with more than half
exceeding The Benchmark for children
a follow-up study confirmed that most
calcium supplements from natural sources
exceeded at least some of the most
stringent lead standards but the levels
only got up to about eight micrograms
where some of the synthetic sources were
up to three times that
a small human study of calcium citrate
was performed in which bone biopsies
were taken before and after about five
years of supplementation no change in
the control group as expected and only a
statistically insignificant increase in
the calcium citrate group though one
can't assume that a given brand is
uniformly safe because some of their
products may have high and others low
lead levels so name brands or recognized
pharmaceutical companies that should
know better are no guarantee but the
good news is that after Decades of
concerned lead levels in calcium
supplements have calmed down so much so
that lead level changes in your blood
taking the average lead contaminated
calcium supplement would be minimal at
this point so these findings on
supplement lead contamination should be
a cause for celebration not alarm or at
least according to a calcium supplement
manufacturer consultant
[Music]
thank you